let's say that you'd like to get this robot to figure out how to pick up objects
이 로봇에게 어떻게 물체를 집어야 하는지 알려준다고 해봅시다
so the goal is to build some system that
그러기 위해서는 어떤 시스템을 만들어야 하는데, 이 시스템은
will use images from the robot's camera
로봇의 카메라를 통해 이미지를 입력받고
position its gripper appropriately and
집게를 적절한 위치로 옮긴 뒤
pick up objects out of a bid
물체를 집어 통 밖으로 꺼내도록 해야 합니다
for instance for a warehousing application
예를 들면 이 시스템은 창고 관리에 쓸 수 있지요
so images come in they go into your method which you're going to design
정리하자면 이미지가 들어오고, 그걸 우리가 만들 방법론에 넣어서
and your method is going to produce xyz coordinates
xyz 좌표를 만들어낸 다음
where the robot is going to put its gripper and attempt to pick up an object
로봇이 집게를 움직여 물체를 집도록 합니다
now you could imagine a number of different approaches to addressing this challenge
그렇다면 이러한 과제를 해결하기 위해 여러가지 접근법을 떠올릴 수 있을 것 같은데요
you could for instance make use of your knowledge of the robotic system
예를 들면 우리가 가진 로봇 시스템 관련 지식을 활용해서
measure the coordinates of the gripper
집게의 좌표를 측정하고
how they relate to the camera
이 좌표와 카메라가 어떻게 관련되어 있는지 측정하고
set up a 3d reconstruction algorithm
3D 재구성 알고리즘을 만들어
to figure out the geometry of the objects
물체의 기하학적 구조를 알아내
and position the gripper appropriately for each grasp
물체를 집을 때마다 집게를 적절하게 위치시킬 수 있습니다
in some cases this will work very well
어떤 경우에는 이 방법이 잘 통할 수 있습니다
for instance if you have a rigid object like this
예를 들면 이렇게 생긴 딱딱한 물체를 집는 경우에는요
the robot will probably put the fingers in the appropriate positions and grasp that object
아마 로봇은 집게를 적절한 위치로 옮겨 물체를 잡을 수 있습니다
but some objects require a little bit more knowledge for instance
그러나 어떤 물체들은 좀 더 많은 지식을 활용해야 합니다
a large heavy object like this
예를 들면 이것처럼 크고 무거운 물체의 경우에요
you'd have to figure out that the center of mass is really concentrated around this bit
이 경우 질량의 중심이 특정 부분 주위에 집중되어 있다는 것을 알아내야 합니다
and pick it up appropriately
그리고 적절하게 물체를 집어야 하죠
and some objects really kind of defy our prior expectations
그리고 어떤 물체들은 우리의 예상을 뒤엎습니다
if you have for example a soft and deformable object
예를 들어 부드럽고 변형 가능한 물체를 잡아야 한다면
a much better way to grasp it is to actually pinch it in the middle
중간 부분을 꼬집는 것처럼 잡는 방식이 물체를 집는 데 있어 훨씬 더 좋은 방법입니다
rather than treating the same as the rigid objects
단단한 물체를 집는 방식에 비해서요
so an alternative that you could consider is to set this up as a learning problem
다른 방법은 이것을 learning problem으로 생각하는 것입니다
but in trying to apply standard supervised machine learning techniques
그러나 여기에 standard supervised machine learning 방법론을 적용하려면
to this task you'll encounter a few challenges
몇 가지 해결해야 할 점들이 있습니다
standard supervised machine learning methods are going to require somebody to provide
standard supervised machine learning 방법론들은 다음과 같은 것을 필요로 하는데요
labeled tuples of images and the corresponding ground truth xyz position for a successful grasp
누군가 labeled tuple of images를 만들고, 로봇이 성공적으로 물체를 집기 위한 ground truth xyz 좌표 위치를 제공해야 합니다
and these are very difficult for humans to provide because we ourselves aren't robots
그런데 우리는 로봇이 아니기 때문에 이런 것들을 하기 어렵습니다
we don't quite have a good intuition for where a robot needs to place its fingers to pick up an object
우리는 로봇이 물체를 집기 위해 집게를 어디에 위치시켜야 하는지에 대한 좋은 직관이 없습니다
so the topic of this class will be to develop reinforcement learning methods
그래서 이 수업의 주제는 이런 종류의 기술을 습득하는 과정을 자동화할 수 있는
that can allow us to automate the process of acquiring skills of this sort
reinforcement learning 방법론을 개발하는 것입니다.
at a very high level you could imagine a reinforcement learning method
개괄적으로 설명하자면 강화학습이란 다음과 같이 생각할 수 있는데요
as utilizing data that is not necessarily ground truth data
데이터를 활용하는데 이것이 꼭 ground truth data여야만 하는 것은 아니고,
that is not necessarily data of good successful behaviors
또 좋은, 성공적인 행동 데이터여야만 하는 것도 아니지만,
but just data that provides experience that tells us
데이터가 현실에서 일어날 수 있는 결과에 대한 경험을 제공해줄 수 있으면 됩니다
so if all these robots can experience a wide variety of objects
그럼 만약 이 모든 로봇들이 다양한 종류의 물체를 집는다고 할 때
picking them up or failing to pick them up
성공하거나 실패하거나 하며 경험을 쌓을 수 있다면
can we use that experience to provide for this grasping system
이 경험들을 물체 집기 시스템에 활용할 수 있을까요?
so in this case we start with data collected autonomously rather than by humans
이 경우에는 사람이 데이터를 제공하는 것이 아니라 데이터를 자동으로 수집하는 것에서 출발합니다
and the data consists of images outputs which are the same xyz tuples
그리고 각 데이터는 동일한 xyz tuple로 이루어진 이미지들로 구성되어 있습니다
and now these tuples are not going to necessarily all be successful
이 tuple 데이터들은 꼭 성공한 데이터여야만 하는 것은 아닙니다
but instead they'll be labeled with their outcome which would be either a success or a failure
대신 그 결과가 성공이냐 실패냐에 따라 그 결과 데이터가 라벨링되어
and this data would be provided to a reinforcement learning algorithm
reinforcement learning algorithm에 제공되고
which would produce a policy that would hopefully perform the task a bit better than
로봇들이 데이터를 수집할 때 했던 것보다 이 과제를 잘 수행할 수 있도록 하는 policy를 만드는 데 쓰입니다
crucially the reinforcement learning algorithm isn't done yet
reinforcement learning algorithm이 아직 끝난 것은 아닙니다
the resulting policy can then be deployed back into the real world
지금까지의 결과로 나온 policy가 현실에 배포되어
to collect additional data that could further improve the behavior
추후 행동을 더 개선시킬 수 있도록 추가 데이터를 수집하게 되죠
so what is reinforcement learning
그래서 reinforcement learning란 무엇이냐
well, fundamentally reinforcement learning is two things
본질적으로 reinforcement learning은 2가지인데요
a mathematical formalism for learning-based decision-making
학습 기반의 의사 결정 방법을 수학적으로 공식화한 것입니다
which allows us to design algorithms
이를 통해 우리가 알고리즘을 설계할 수 있도록 해주죠
and an approach for learning decision making and control from experience from data
그리고 데이터로부터의 경험을 통해 의사결정이나 제어 방법을 학습할 수 있도록 하는 접근법입니다
rather than relying on the controller or policy itself being designed by hand
제어기 또는 수동으로 설계한 policy에 의존하는 것 대신에요
how is reinforcement learning different from other machine learning topics
reinforcement learning이 다른 machine learning 주제들과는 어떻게 다른가 하면
well if we consider standard or supervised machine learning
만약 우리가 standard (supervised) machine learning을 생각해보면
we typically make a number of assumptions for example we'll typically assume
일반적으로 몇 가지 가정을 합니다. 예를 들어 우리에게
that we're given data consisting of inputs x and outputs y
input x와 output y로 구성된 데이터가 주어지고
and our goal is to learn to predict y from x to essentially acquire some function f of x that gives us y
우리의 목표가 x로부터 y를 예측할 수 있도록 학습하는 것이라 하면 이는 본질적으로 y를 결과값으로 가지는 x에 대한 함수 f를 구하는 것이죠
not only do we assume that the data is actually labeled
이 때 우리는 데이터가 실제로 라벨링되어 있을 것이라 가정할 뿐만 아니라
but we also assume typically the data is i.i.d. which means independent and identically distributed
해당 데이터가 i.i.d. (independent and identically distributed) 가정을 만족한다고 가정합니다
this means that the output y that we produce for a given input x
이는 주어진 input x를 가지고 만든 output y가
is not going to have any effect on other input specs
다른 input spec에 대해 어떠한 영향도 미치지 않는다는 것을 의미합니다
and of course we have to assume that we know the ground truth outputs in training
또한 우리는 학습 과정에서 ground truth output을 알고 있을 거라 가정해야만 하는데요
in contrast reinforcement learning handles situations where the data is not i.i.d.
이와 반대로 reinforcement learning은 데이터가 i.i.d가 아닌 상황을 다루는데
in the sense that previous outputs will influence future inputs
과거의 output이 미래의 input에 영향을 주기 때문입니다
so the action that you took before will affect what you see next
그래서 이전에 했던 action이 미래에 관찰할 수 있는 대상에 영향을 줍니다
and the ground truth answer is typically not known
그리고 ground truth answer는 일반적으로 알 수 없습니다
in fact instead all you really find out is whether you succeed or failed or more generally what reward you received
사실 그 대신에 알아내야 하는 것은 성공 또는 실패 여부이고, 혹은 좀 더 일반적으로 말하자면 어떤 reward를 얻었는지입니다
so in reinforcement learning we model a decision-making system as an interaction between an agent and an environment
그래서 우리는 reinforcement learning에서 agent와 environment가 상호작용하는 의사결정 시스템을 모델링합니다
the agent makes decisions which we refer to as actions
agent는 우리가 action이라 부르는 결정을 만들어내고
and the environment responds to those decisions with observations
environment는 이런 결정들에 대해 반응하여
and crucially this process is repeated multiple times over the course of an episode
그리고 결정적으로 이러한 과정은 한 episode에서 여러 번 반복됩니다
reinforcement learning can be finite horizon which means that this is repeated a fixed number of times
reinforcement learning에는 이것이 유한 번 반복되는 finite horizon 방식과
or infinite horizon which means that this decision-making cycle goes on forever
의사결정 주기가 무한히 반복되는 infinite horizon 방식이 있습니다
here are some examples of how we could embed real world problems into this reinforcement framework
여기 우리가 어떻게 현실의 문제를 reinforcement framework로 가져올 수 있는지에 대한 몇 가지 예시가 있습니다
if you're trying to teach a dog how to perform a particular trick
만약 개에게 어떤 행동을 가르치고 싶다면
maybe the dog's actions are its muscle contractions
아마 개의 action은 근육의 수축이 될 것이고
its observations consist of its senses its sight and smell
개의 observation은 개가 느끼는 시각적 자극이나 냄새로 이루어질 것입니다
and the reward is the treat that you give it when it does what you want or withhold it when it does not do what you want
그리고 reward는 우리가 원하는 것을 개가 했을 때 개에게 주는 간식이거나, 우리가 원하는 것을 하지 않을 경우 간식을 주지 않는 것이 됩니다
if you are using reinforcement learning to train a robot
만약 로봇을 reinforcement learning을 활용해 학습시키고 싶다면
maybe its actions are motor currents or torques
아마 로봇의 action은 모터의 전류나 회전이 될 것이고
its observations are inputs from its sensors like its camera
observation은 로봇의 카메라 같은 센서로부터 들어오는 입력,
and the rewards here might consist of some measure of task success for example
reward는 과제를 성공적으로 수행한 정도가 됩니다
if you'd like the robot to learn how to run
예를 들어 로봇에게 달리는 것을 가르치고 싶다면
the measure of success would be how fast it's running
성공적으로 수행한 정도는 얼마나 빠르게 달렸는가를 측정하여 구할 수 있습니다
but reinforced learning is not limited just to dogs and robots
그러나 reinforcement learning은 단순히 개나 로봇에 한정되지 않습니다
you could also imagine applying reinforcement learning for instance
reinforcement learning은 재고관리와 같은 운용과학(Operation Research) 분야의 문제에도 적용할 수 있습니다
where the actions will consist of decisions about what to purchase
이 문제에서 action은 무엇을 구매할지에 대한 결정들로 이루어지고
the observations might consist of the inventory levels at the current point in time
observation은 각 시점의 재고 수준으로 구성됩니다
and the reward might consist of the net profit that you're earning
그리고 reward는 아마 얻을 수 있는 순이익으로 구성되겠죠
so you could imagine applying reinforcement settings to settings like this and also many others
그래서 이와 같은 문제 또는 다른 문제에 reinforcement learning을 적용해볼 수 있습니다
you could imagine applying reinforcement learning to learn complex physical tasks
복잡한 물리적 과제를 reinforcement learning을 활용해 학습하는 것도 생각해 볼 수 있겠죠
like for example getting this robotic hand to use a tool to hammer in a nail
예를 들어 로봇 손을 활용해 망치로 못을 박거나 하는 식으로요
you could imagine using reinforcement learning to automatically acquire unexpected solutions like in this video
이 비디오처럼 reinforcement learning을 사용하여 예상치 못한 해결책을 자동으로 찾도록 하는 것도 생각해볼 수 있습니다
of a q learning algorithm playing the atari game breakout
Q-learning algorithm을 활용하여 벽돌깨기를 하는 영상인데요
initially this learned policy plays the game the way you might expect
처음에는 학습된 policy가 예상할 수 있는 방식으로 게임을 하지만
but it actually figured out that if you can get the ball to bounce up there and bounce around for a while
나중에는 공을 위쪽으로 올릴 경우 한동안 위에서 공이 튄다는 것을 발견하게 됩니다
you can get a lot more points than you would otherwise
다른 방식으로 얻을 수 있는 점수보다 훨씬 더 많은 점수를 얻을 수 있죠
you can use reinforcement in the real world
우리는 실세계에서 reinforcement learning을 사용할 수 있습니다
so coming back to the grasping example from before
다시 물건 집는 로봇 예시로 돌아가보죠
you can use robots that practice picking up a wide range of different objects
다양한 물체를 집는 연습을 하는 로봇을 사용할 수 있습니다.
and from having done that practicing figure out complex skills
그리고 그러한 연습을 함으로써 복잡한 기술을 하는 법을 알아낼 수 있습니다
like for example that if objects are positioned close together you need to push them apart a little bit
예를 들어 만약 물체가 가까이 위치해 있다면 조금 밀어서 서로 떨어지게 한다던가 말이죠
and then pick up the individual singulated objects
그리고 나서 각 물체를 집고
and then you can take apart all these pieces one by one
각 조각들을 하나하나 떨어뜨려 놓을 수 있죠
you could also figure out that
그럼 다음과 같은 것도 알 수 있는데
you know if you attempt to pick up an object successfully that's good you should put it away
만약 물체를 집으려는 시도가 성공하면 바로 치우면 되지만
but if you tried to pick it up and you missed and slipped a little bit
만약 물체를 집는 데 실패하고 놓치게 되면
then it's better to try again reposition your gripper and go in for another try
집게를 다시 위치시켜 다른 시도를 하는 것이 좋습니다
you could also train the policy such that
또한 이런 policy를 학습하여
it can pick up a wide range of different objects
다양한 종류의 다른 물체를 집을 수 있게 되는데
so in the same way that we can see generalization in all sorts of computer vision applications
computer vision 응용 분야에서의 일반화를 볼 수 있는 것과 같은 방식으로
we can see generalization in reinforcement learning systems
reinforcement learning system에서도 일반화를 볼 수 있습니다
even generalization some perturbations
심지어 누군가 집게가 잡은 물체를 건드려서 다시 시도해야 하는, 방해하는 경우에도 generalization이 가능합니다
but of course it's not just for games and robots i mentioned that you could use reinforced learning for things like inventory management
하지만 물론 게임이나 로봇에만 해당하는 것은 아닙니다 아까 언급한 것처럼 재고 관리 같은 분야에 reinforcement learning을 사용할 수 있습니다
here's an example this is actually done by Cathy Wu who's a phd student here at berkeley and is now a professor at mit
Cathy Wu의 연구가 그 예시입니다 여기 Berkeley에서 박사과정을 하고 현재는 MIT에 교수로 가 있지요
applying reinforcement learning to traffic control so in this video the white cars are kind of simulated humans
교통정리에 reinforcement learning을 적용한 것인데요 이 비디오를 보면 하얀색 차들은 사람이 운전하는 것을 시뮬레이션한 것입니다
and the red car is an autonomous car and
그리고 빨간색 차는 자율주행 차입니다
this car's goal is to regulate traffic so all these cars drive in a circle as smoothly as possible
이 차의 목표는 이 모든 차들이 최대한 원활하게 원을 돌며 주행할 수 있도록 교통정리를 하는 것입니다
and what you can see here is that the autonomous car is actually going to dynamically decide
그리고 여기서 볼 수 있는 것은 자율주행차가 실제로 동적으로 의사결정을 하여
to slow down or speed up so as to keep all the entire traffic circle going
속도를 줄이거나 높여서 전반적인 교통 수준을 유지한다는 것입니다
so initially some traffic jams form automatically but after a while
그래서 처음에는 약간의 교통체증이 자동적으로 발생하지만 시간이 지나면
this autonomous car figures out that it should regulate the flow of traffic
이 자율주행차가 교통의 흐름을 조절해는 방법을 알아내고
adjusts its speed gives the car ahead of it a little bit more room
속도를 조절하여 그 앞에 있는 차와 좀 더 거리를 둡니다
and as a result keeps the entire circle of cars flowing much more smoothly
그리고 그 결과 전체적인 차들이 훨씬 더 원활하게 주행할 수 있도록 해줍니다
here's a more complex example so here there's this figure eight situation
이건 좀 더 복잡한 예시인데 8자형 도로가 있고
and first you're going to see just the white car so there's no autonomous car here
처음에는 하얀색 차만 보이실 겁니다 무인자동차는 여기 없습니다
so this is just kind of what the simulated humans do on their own they kind of bunch up at this intersection
즉 이것은 사람들이 수동으로 운전하는 것을 시뮬레이션한 것인데 이 교차로 부분에 모여들게 되죠
ended up having to wait for each other for quite a bit
그리고 결국 서로를 기다리며 꽤나 시간을 쓰게 됩니다
but once we put in an autonomous car shown here in red
그러나 우리가 빨간색 자율주행차를 투입해보면
now this autonomous car again its job is to regulate the flow of traffic so that
이 자율주행차가 교통정리 작업을 수행하기 시작해
everyone goes at a steady speed what it will actually do is it will wait
모두가 일정한 속도로 가게 만들죠 이것이 실제로 하는 일은 잠시 기다려서
so the last car clears the intersection and then have this kind of snake of cars
가장 마지막에 있는 차가 교차로를 지나간 후 차들의 대열이 그 시간에 맞춰 교차로를 통과하도록 하는 것입니다
so that no one has to wait at the intersection of the stop sign
이를 통해 아무도 정지 표지판이 있는 교차로에서 기다릴 필요가 없게 됩니다
all right
좋습니다